good
too so here's where uh we saw the these
are the stochastic differential
equations and what this says is the
difference in
U is going to be some
function of the current XU and
Y and if that's all we had if this is
all we had then we would have a
differential
equation this would say the update is
given by the change is Su is determined
by X U and Y and what the specific rule
for determining the change is can be you
know up for discussion but the we're
describing the change through a rule
that depends on the current
information what makes it a stochastic
differential equation is that it has
this additional Omega sub U term
um where Omega subu is a random
variable so we're not always going to
get exactly the same change based on the
current
information but rather we will get a
rule that is applied and then some
initial stochastic noise is added
on so we will not just will not generate
a single trajectory like an ordinary
differential equation would um rather
it's going to generate a bunch of
different possible trajectories and each
of these different possible trajectories
will have a probability associated with
it and that's going to be dependent
on what the
original uh deterministic update rule f
subu
is and what the original stochastic
process Omega subu is so this is you
know incredibly General
uh
and if we plugged in specific fs and
specific omegas then we might see
specific
results but this is an example of
something that we talked about a little
bit last week which is a stochastic
differential equation
and the point here I don't have
tremendous like I've never taught a
class on these um I've seen them a
little bit in my work on cryptocurrency
Consulting Financial modeling um but
mainly I know this from seeing other
people do it and so this is something
I'm actively working to try to
understand
better so one thing that I find is
helpful is to see if is there a specific
example of this that I can come up
with so what would it look like if I
um came up with like what is a
stochastic
process do I know an example of a
stochastic process do I know uh so one
of the the PE things you can do here is
actually done in the book you can start
removing information
and
seeing what
pieces you actually have because for me
as someone with my brain um I get
overwhelmed by information when it
occurs in like large amorphous
chunks and so what I have to try to do
is give it a
structure and I liked how the book did
this with the expected free energy this
has five parts right but then you start
looking at what if I drop this part what
if I drop this part what if I drop these
two parts and maybe I understand this
part where I just dropped two it's it's
uh I don't have a name for it it's like
you cover
up part of the information and you see
if you can can grasp that single
piece so I do have a large principle for
this I've developed which is called the
two confusion principle or the um
stepladder princip
principle and it says try not to be try
to go one step at a
time and you'll call it the single
uncertainty
principle or step ladder
principle so when you're trying to climb
these things resist the temptation to
like jump four steps at once go one step
at a time
find one thing you are uncertain
about and fill in the one fill in that
one
step so I developed this principle when
I was trying to teach machine learning
or when I was teaching machine learning
and I was explaining uh or we were
discussing different models like we're
discussing a random Forest we're
discussing a boosted tree
whatever and then we're looking at data
we're trying to look at data
on
um stock
prices well there's a problem here
because if we don't if we don't know
much about stock prices and we don't
know much about random forests we have
almost no hope of understanding anything
because we don't have a starting
point we don't have a concrete way of
like how if I understand one I can use
it to understand the other
so this is a principle I've been trying
to
use I understand differential equations
don't understand stochastic differential
equations so I'm trying to leverage
whatever I do understand about the
deterministic case to advance to that
next step of my
understanding and a lot of times just
stopping and saying okay what am I
confused about what what of this do I
not understand
um there's something psychological that
happens
here because if we don't have any uh
contact with the familiar at all our
brains tend to go
into modes of uncertainty anxiety and
then we it's easy it's easy when we get
in this uncertain place for the
uncertainties to begin to spiral
that's something I don't know if you all
have experienced it's not pleasant but
like when you're just imagining things
you can start to imagine basically
anything whereas if you make contact
with some aspect of concrete
reality then suddenly you have a
grounding
point so are there any any things that
we're that we're
seeing where maybe we could find like
the next step of what we would want to
fill in or where we're confident up to a
certain
point and it's okay one of the things
for me at least it's okay you have no
idea how deep these things could go
none of us
do so we got a few weeks ago we were
looking at the different base of the
logarithms and how that could change the
answer we got if we're trying to come to
consensus on what an answer should be
but we're using different bases of
logarithms you know
that's that's a place where we could
need to fill something
in the key though all of this that I'm
trying to do is not just okay let's
review these symbolic manipulations or
let's prove this theorem although those
things might be important but there's
also this highly metacognitive strategic
aspect of how do we decide what we're
going to think about and how we're going
to think about it to leverage and
uh I have all these things I've
developed this this toolkit
for getting to math mathematical
understanding from wherever we're
starting and I'm trying to share those
tools as well as hopefully using them to
to gain some
insight so I'm be quiet for a few
minutes and see if youall have any
thoughts on what I've said or any
questions as to specific things you'd
like to dive
into
e e
boiler's
number and
when you would
use the natural logarithm versus other
logarithms and why yeah why would you
use why would you use a particular base
for a particular
logarithm
um
Oilers I mean it's called the natural
algorithm it's kind of a copout but it's
the rate at which things tend to grow
naturally um there's also it's also
useful because e to the x is its own
derivative and so sometimes that cleans
things up where you don't need an extra
constant hanging
around
um so let me talk about why would you
use log base 2
why why would you want to use two for
the logarithm logarithmic
base so computer scientists are going to
use log base 2 because they're working
with switches
right and things are either on or
off and so it makes sense in terms of
the kind of
also they're often working with trees to
model that so log base 2 comes from
things tending to grow like binary
trees and sort of like when you get to
the next level there's twice as
much so using log base too kind of helps
you know what level you are on in this
in a binary growth process roughly
speaking um so why would you use log
base 10
what's the advantage or what intuition
comes from
using why would we use log base 10 we
have 10 fingers and so the metric system
is based
on
um so are you working at the order are
we looking at kilometers or are we
looking at centimeters or millimeters
log base 10 does a very a good job of
telling us immediately kind of what
scale we're on where scale is a metric
system type
scale or number of digits in the number
here we're looking at number of
bits what's the advantage of log base
e
um
well not sure I've ever thought about
that
before thought way more about the other
two uh types of logarithms and even
though as a mathematician I use log log
base e all the
time uh I'm not sure why that's the my
go-to it has these nice properties there
are some nice properties about e to the
X and e as a number some limiting things
um like if you are doing
continuous continuous growth continuous
compounding e kind of naturally pops
out but as to what intuition it gives in
terms of the I don't have intuition for
it the same way I do for what log base 2
and log base 10 tell me so maybe that's
an interesting thing we could
um put in our sack to think about for
the future
of how like how intuitively does log Bas
E help us and if anybody has thought on
that I'm happy to consider
them put that in the
it's usually just important that once we
pick a base we're consistent with it or
that we are clear on what base we
picked but I'm sure there is some
intuition here
um another technique that's useful here
or has been useful to me at least in
terms of keeping things approachable and
concrete just like active inference with
these mathematical things a lot of times
there's a high road and a low
road and or maybe we can think of it as
abstract and concrete
so with all of these equations you know
maybe some people have sufficient
experience that they see it and it
immediately means something to them and
there's really no need for them to do
else I don't do anything else I don't
you know I can't be inside other
people's brains and know how they're
thinking um I do know that a difference
between mathematical thinking and other
types of thinking in my opinion is that
there's really
uh
less
discrepancy between what is said and
what is
represented and what I mean by that is
in like political speech you can talk
about all these very abstract Concepts
like equality or Freedom or
whatever you can come up with you know
very elaborate and nice sounding
phrases but they lack any real reference
so when we come
to what does freedom actually mean what
does freedom look like then it becomes
its own huge discussion that is
ultimately
unresolvable and math doesn't work that
way when you say something
mathematically it's intended to have a
very precise meaning and to be
unambiguous and
uncontroversial as to what the term is
representing so one thing that I has
been helpful to me in looking at these
things is to look for running examples
or for things I can plug into the theory
to sort of see how it would
work so one um thing with the with these
different discussions of variational
free energy and expected free energy is
you can just think about a common
situation where you would have two
different probability
distributions and and then calculate and
see what would the difference be or what
would these quantities be for these two
different situations that you could
consider so as we use it over and over
again it can become more concrete to
us
um so a couple of weeks ago something we
started to
do and uh did
not did not arrive at but we could we
could go back to it is looking at this
for two different
coins if you think that one coin if you
think that you have a 50/50 coin but you
actually have a biased coin
how much uh what do these things look
like what does cobac Liber Divergence
look
like and that was the one we were
actually looking
at
so if we're approximating a a biased
coin with a Fair coin
how do these numbers change as the bias
gets more and more away from 50/50
whereas the distribution gets further
and further
from
um uh equal on each outcome
so I think it would be worth going back
to that if you have any interest in
doing
it hello we have a newcomer how are you
cool so I'll be back in just a moment
and we can go through the
different
um we can go through koback lebl
Divergence for two coins and then we
maybe we could look at other models and
and see what that looks
like
e
e e
okay so let's define our two
distributions here we're going to have
two different
coins
and let's have P be the fair one and U
let's have actually let's have P be the
bias one and let's have q be the fair
one
it's thicker
so Q is going to be the biased
coin and let's take
this and so p
is distribution Where Heads has some
prob heads has a probability of uh 5050
and Tails has a probability of
5050 and
Q I don't know what the probability of H
is so let's just say that it's the
number
B and then the probability of tails is 1
minus
B and I'm using B here to stand for bias
so let's I'm going to use the second
formulation
[Music]
for computing
F of
q y and I'm mainly going to be focused
on the What's called the complexity term
here so the complexity this d sub KL Q
ofx
double line P of X is the cback Leer
Divergence
of
this
so my memory serves this is
equal
to the sum over our possible
outcomes let me just look it up since
I'm not remembering it immediately
one thing that's fun is the way the Q
and the p in the book are uh reversed
from the Q and the p and the formula so
I have to make that mental
switch um so this is going to be the sum
over Q
ofx sum overx and X of Q
ofx times the
log of Q ofx over p ofx
and so this sum over x and x is like the
H and the T so we're going to have an H
term and a t
term
so we have q of H
log Q of H over P of
h
plus q
t
log e
U of T over h of
T so this will be
so Q of H was whatever my bias is I
don't it's a value it's a number B okay
so then log
of
B over
0.5 Plus
1 -
B
log of 1us
B over
0.5 so this depends on
B but we can now um that's all it
depends on is the probability of heads
so we can make a plot of this where we
have this quantity is the output D is
the output and it's its function of B
and it will be equal to
this and what this could give us is an
intuitive sense
of for instance how quickly the coolback
leeler Divergence grows when as the bias
gets further away from
1/2 as the coin becomes less and less
Fair
um
so see if I can plot that
with I don't think I can plot it with
D's and B's and Desmos but let's try
anyway and if I can't we'll just switch
the variables to F and
X for the
standard D of B equal to
B time log B /
0.5 1 minus
B times the log
ofus B desired by 0 2 five
this is what it looks like it's
roughly no it's concave up symmetric
about
0.5 maximum
value for this base a loger them look
like
it's have to take a limit looks like
it's
approaching
0.29 maybe 0.3
what this tells us is this quantity of
cack leeler
Divergence um between these two which is
also called
complexity then we can look at the
accuracy the accuracy depends
on data y
and for me I feel like okay if I did
this and I looked at this and I now know
that this quantity looks like this for
two coins I can understand
intuitively if I have a biased coin but
I think it's fair um the complexity gets
higher and higher as the coin moves
further and further away and I can can
kind of see the shape of how that
happens and so that's something that's
helpful to me and I try to I'm trying to
do that with all of these things to come
up with some simple concrete calculation
I can
do that connects to something I feel I
understand so that it's not just a a
huge pile of
symbols and then I've also noticed in
looking at the appendix that this there
are times where this pops up as a actual
calculation in a more relevant context
for instance where people are like let's
let's find the complexity of using one
distribution to approximate another or
let's calculate something about that so
having done this once I feel more
prepared to do it
again and that is called the poia
principle it's named after um George POA
who
wrote how to solve
it he
said if there's a problem you don't feel
comfortable with there's a smaller
problem that's related that you do feel
comfortable with it and you can solve
that one instead as a starting
point in this case the problem we worked
through is like just finding an
immediate concrete example to try to
latch on to but that's the whole
strategy is to create things in chunks
so that it never becomes totally
overwhelming
okay is there anything y'all would like
to do that with for next time uh that's
currently in the textbook
where you'd like for us to try
to go through it in in a concrete way
and make it more
um what's the word less abstract less
vague hello sorry I uh do can you hear
me I can hear you yes yes
uh thank you for doing this I'm um yeah
I was a bit late so I didn't hear what
you said in the beginning and it's the
first time I'm here uh so maybe I'm
saying things that are redundant with
what you've done before so uh but um for
me it was especially chapter 4 which was
very unclear how things uh well kept
together somehow like there were some
jumps in the it's a while ago that I
looked at it so I would have to look
again to be very precise in what I don't
understand
um but also in this chapter the um the
three formulations of the the free
energy uh how one goes to another uh is
totally unclear to me like how the these
derivations uh how that they actually
are the same that
was it wasn't it wasn't clear to me at
first either actually last week was
unclear but I
guess yeah last so we this is like the
third or fourth of these sessions we've
done and we're still trying we're still
working through exactly what a structure
or format looks like so um I'm just
trying to go through things that might
be helpful both in terms of if people
have specific questions I'll do what I
can to figure out where the information
is or what we can do with it and then
also is I'm I'm not um I have a strong
math background but I don't have a
strong background in all of the math in
the active inference and I I'm learning
active inference so a lot of times it's
like oh okay I read this this week and
here's how I tried to understand it just
sharing things that worked for me or
might might work for other people our
goal is to get is to unstuck ourselves
as much as we can and just have a a
richer exper experience with it the the
specific thing you're talking about with
the proofs of the equivalence of the
different types of variational free or
the different calculations of
variational free energy we actually did
that last week in detail right I can
share that link uh with you and then
yeah which will be very nice it from
there um are you on the Discord I can
put in the Discord
and I think you can uh is there a
Discord I not on the Discord I am on the
Koda ah okay I will add it to the Koda
then a link to it on the Koda and um I
have my own page which I need to start
using more for these discs and
uh but I I'm not very acquainted with
Koda yet so um yes I'll try to find it
and then let me let me see because uh
yeah I'll try to find it too and um if
you come back next week I can be sure to
have the link ready for you okay thank
you very
[Music]
much wa I'm going to check to be certain
that I can be there next week otherwise
it's the week after I guess yeah
uh yeah that should be fine next week
I'll try to be there cool um so in the
Cod is there a Discord that you said uh
yeah there is a Discord let me see if I
can drop I'll drop you an invite via
private message in the
chat thank
you
cool well uh if you don't mind my asking
how do you pronounce your name
friend uh my name is yoris yoris yoris
Heros okay okay yours is that I hope yes
that's
fine have heard many many variants by
now so it's fine
whatever I I'll do my best um youris
um yeah so I was actually starting this
session by saying I was low on
Preparation like last week I had all the
proofs written out and some exercises we
were going to do together and this week
it just didn't happen that way but if
people can let me know specific
questions ahead of time I usually try to
prepare something and if not we just
kind of show up and and freestyle
it because okay
great anyone have any other thoughts
they'd like to share before we close
okay well I am getting the Discord
invite I like your shirt oh thank
you and thank you for today yeah thank
you all if we keep coming we'll
keep we'll keep
learning yeah so if anyone is not in the
Discord and you would like to be I'm
putting a link in the chat right
now and I hope you all will come again
next week and if you let me know
questions in the Discord I'll try to
think about more specific things that we
could
discuss thank you very much see you next
week then see next week